<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<passages>
    <passage>
        <description>
            <idPassage>21</idPassage>
            <documentType>expository</documentType>
            <area>history</area>
            <topic>conventions</topic>
        </description>
        <paragraphs>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText>The canopy ,the upper level of the trees in the rain forest, holds a plethora of climbing
                    mammals of moderately large size, which may include monkeys, cats, civets, and
                    porcupines. Smaller species, including such rodents as mice and small squirrels ,are not
                    as prevalent overall in high tropical canopies as they are in most habitats globally.
                     Small mammals, being warm blooded, suffer hardship in the exposed and turbulent
                    environment of the uppermost trees. Because a small body has more surface area per unit
                    of weight than a large one of similar shape, it gains or loses heat more swiftly. Thus, in
                    the trees, where shelter from heat and cold may be scarce and conditions may fluctuate, a
                    small mammal may have trouble maintaining its body temperature.
                    
                    
 </paragraphText>
                <sentences>
                    <sentence>
                        <sentenceText>The canopy ,the upper level of the trees in the rain forest, holds a plethora of climbing
                            mammals of moderately large size, which may include monkeys, cats, civets, and
                            porcupines .</sentenceText>
                        <semanticRelation>PartWhole/ObjectComponent</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>ObjectComponent(tree,canopy)</assertion>

<semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
<context>no</context>
<assertion>hyponym(mammals,monkeys)</assertion>
<assertion>hyponym(mammals,cats)</assertion>
<assertion>hyponym(mammals,civets)</assertion>
<assertion>hyponym(mammals,porcupines)</assertion>


                    </sentence>
                
            
                </sentences>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText> Small size makes it easy to scramble among twigs and branches in the canopy for
                    insects, flowers, or fruit, but small mammals are surpassed, in the competition for food,
                    by large ones that have their own tactics for browsing among food-rich twigs. The weight
                    of a gibbon (a small ape) hanging below a branch arches the terminal leaves down so that
                    fruit-bearing foliage drops toward the gibbon’s face. Walking or leaping species of a
                    similar or even larger size access the outer twigs either by snapping off and retrieving the
                    whole branch or by clutching stiff branches with the feet or tail and plucking food with
                    their hands.
                    
                    
                    
</paragraphText>
                 <sentences>
              
                 </sentences>
        </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText>  Small climbing animals may reach twigs readily, but it is harder for them than for large
                    climbing animals to cross the wide gaps from on tree crown to the next that typify the
                    high canopy. A macaque or gibbon can hurl itself farther than a mouse can: it can achieve
                    a running start, and it can more effectively use a branch as a springboard, even bouncing
                    on a climb several times before jumping. The forward movement of a small animal is
                    seriously reduced by the air friction against the relatively large surface area of its body.
                    Finally, for the many small mammals that supplement their insect diet with fruits or seeds
                    an inability to span open gaps between tree crowns may be problematic, since trees that
                    yield these foods can be sparse.

        </paragraphText>
        <sentences>
           
        </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    
        </paragraphs>
    
    
        <questionAnswerBlock>
            <questions>
                <question>
                    <questionText>Which of the following animals is less common  in the upper canopy than in other environments?
                        
 </questionText>
                    <answers>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>   Monkeys
	</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>collectionMember(forest,monkeys)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>Cats
                                	</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>collectionMember(forest,cats)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>Porcupines				</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>collectionMember(forest,porcupines)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText> Mice</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>

                    </answers>
                </question>
                <question>
                    <questionText>The word “typify” in line 19 is closest in meaning to
                    
                        
 </questionText>
                    <answers>
                        <answer>   resemble
                            </answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText> protect
                            </answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText> characterize
	</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            
                            <assertion>synonym(typify,characterize)</assertion>
                          
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText> divide	</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>

                        </answer>
                        
                    </answers>
                </question>
            </questions>
        </questionAnswerBlock>
    </passage>
    
    <!--- pasaje 22 -->
    
    
    <passage>
        <description>
            <idPassage>22</idPassage>
            <documentType>argumentative</documentType>
            <area>history</area>
            <topic>literature</topic>
        </description>
        <paragraphs>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText>          During the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, almost nothing was written about the
                    contributions of women during the colonial period and the early history of the newly
                    formed United States. Lacking the right to vote and absent from the seats of power, women
                    were not considered an important force in history. Anne Bradstreet wrote some significant
                    poetry in the seventeenth century, Mercy Otis Warren produced the best contemporary
                    history of the American Revolution, and Abigail Adams penned important letters showing
                    she exercised great political influence over her husband, John, the second President of the
                    United States. But little or no notice was taken of these contributions. During these
                    centuries, women remained invisible in history books.
                    
                   
                </paragraphText>
                <sentences>
                    
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText>           Throughout the nineteenth century, this lack of visibility continued, despite the efforts
                    of female authors writing about women. These writers, like most of their male counterparts,
                    were amateur historians. Their writings were celebratory in nature, and they were uncritical
                    in their selection and use of sources.
                    
                    
                </paragraphText>
                <sentences>
                    
                </sentences>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText>         During the nineteenth century, however, certain feminists showed a keen sense of
                    history by keeping records of activities in which women were engaged. National, regional,
                    and local women’s organizations compiled accounts of their doings. Personal
                    correspondence, newspaper clippings, and souvenirs were saved and stored. These sources
                    from the core of the two greatest collections of women’s history in the United States one at
                    the Elizabeth and Arthur Schlesinger Library at Radcliffe College, and the other the Sophia
                    Smith Collection at Smith College. Such sources have provided valuable materials for later
                    Generations of historians.
                    
                    

                </paragraphText>
                <sentences>
                    
                </sentences>
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                <id_paragraph>4</id_paragraph>
                <paragraphText>          Despite the gathering of more information about ordinary women during the nineteenth
                    Century, most of the writing about women conformed to the “great women” theory of
                    History, just as much of mainstream American history concentrated on “great men.” To
                    demonstrate that women were making significant contributions to American life, female
                    authors singled out women leaders and wrote biographies, or else important women
                    produced their autobiographies. Most of these leaders were involved in public life as
                    reformers, activists working for women’s right to vote, or authors, and were not
                    representative at all of the great of ordinary woman. The lives of ordinary people
                    continued, generally, to be untold in the American histories being published.

                </paragraphText>
                <sentences>
                    
                </sentences>
            </paragraph>


        </paragraphs>
        
        
        <questionAnswerBlock>
            <questions>
                <question>
                    <questionText>    The word “contemporary” in line 5 means that the history was
                        
                    </questionText>
                    <answers>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>   informative
                                

                            </answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>written at that time
                                                          </answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>synonym(contemporary,writtenAtTheTime)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>    thoughtful
                                
		</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>faultfinding</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        
                    </answers>
                </question>
                <question>
                    <questionText>  In the last paragraph, the author mentions all of the following as possible roles of nineteenth-century “great women” EXCEPT
                        
                        
                    </questionText>
                    <answers>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText> authors
                            </answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>agentGoal(woman, author)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>reformers
                               
                                
                            </answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>agentGoal(woman, reformer)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>   activists for women’s rights			</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>agentGoal(woman, activist)</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        <answer>
                            <answerText>politicians		</answerText>
                            <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                            <context>no</context>
                            <assertion>no</assertion>
                        </answer>
                        
                    </answers>
                </question>
                
               
                
               
            </questions>
        </questionAnswerBlock>
    </passage>

<!--- pasaje 33 -->
<passage>
    <description>
        <idPassage>33</idPassage>
        <documentType>expository</documentType>
        <area>art</area>
        <topic>art nouveau</topic>
    </description>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>         The end of the nineteenth century and the early years of the twentieth century were
                marked by the development of an international Art Nouveau style, characterized by sinuous
                lines, floral and vegetable motifs, and soft evanescent coloration. The Art Nouveau style
                was an eclectic one, bringing together elements of Japanese art, motifs of ancient cultures,
                 and natural forms. The glass objects of this style were elegant in outline, although often
                deliberately distorted, with pale or iridescent surfaces. A favored device of the style was to
                imitate the iridescent surface seen on ancient glass that had been buried. Much of the Art
                Nouveau glass produced during the years of its greatest popularity had been generically
                termed “art glass.” Art glass was intended for decorative purposes and relied for its effect
                 on carefully chosen color combinations and innovative techniques.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                <sentence>
                    <sentenceText>  The end of the nineteenth century and the early years of the twentieth century were
                        marked by the development of an international Art Nouveau style, characterized by sinuous
                        lines, floral and vegetable motifs, and soft evanescent coloration.</sentenceText>
                    <semanticRelation>PartWhole/ObjectComponent</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>component(ArtNouveau,sinousLines)</assertion>
                     <assertion>component(ArtNouveau,floralMotifs)</assertion>
                      <assertion>component(ArtNouveau,vegetableMotifs)</assertion>
                       <assertion>component(ArtNouveau,softEvanescentColoration)</assertion>
                </sentence>
                
                
            </sentence>
        </sentences>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
        <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
        <paragraphText> France produced a number of outstanding exponents of the Art Nouveau style; among
            the most celebrated was Emile Galle (1846-1904). In the United States, Louis Comfort
            Tiffany (1843-1933) was the most noted exponent of this style, producing a great variety of
            glass forms and surfaces, which were widely copied in their time and are highly prized
            today. Tiffany was a brilliant designer, successfully combining ancient Egyptian, Japanese,
            and Persian motifs.
            
            
            
            
            
        </paragraphText>
        <sentences>
            
            
    </sentences>

    </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>
                The Art Nouveau style was a major force in the decorative arts from 1895 until 1915,
                although its influence continued throughout the mid-1920’s. It was eventually to be
                overtaken by a new school of thought known as Functionalism that had been present since
                the turn of the century. At first restricted to a small avant-garde group of architects and
                designers, Functionalism emerged as the dominant influence upon designers after the First
                World War. The basic tenet of the movement-that function should determine from-was
                not a new concept. Soon a distinct aesthetic code evolved: from should be simple, surfaces
                plain, and any ornament should be based on geometric relationships. This new design
                concept, coupled with the sharp postwar reactions to the styles and conventions of the
                preceding decades, created an entirely new public taste which caused Art Nouveau types of
                glass to fall out of favor. The new taste demanded dramatic effects of contrast, stark outline
                and complex textural surfaces.

                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                
                </sentences>
            </paragraph>


    </paragraphs>


    <questionAnswerBlock>
        <questions>
            <question>
                <questionText>The word “prized” in line 14 is closest in meaning to
                    
                    
                    
 </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>valued	                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(prized,valued)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>preserved
                           
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>
                            <answerText>universal					</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> uncommon		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
            <question>
                <questionText>The word “overtaken” in line 19 is closest in meaning to
                    
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> surpassed
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>inclined
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> expressed
		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>applied	</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(overtaken,applied)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>





                   </questions>
    </questionAnswerBlock>
</passage>
<!--- pasaje 34 -->
<passage>
    <description>
        <idPassage>34</idPassage>
        <documentType>expository</documentType>
        <area>geography</area>
        <topic>glaciers</topic>
    </description>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>              During most of their lives, surge glaciers behave like normal glaciers, traveling perhaps
                only a couple of inches per day. However, at intervals of 10 to 100 years, these glaciers
                move forward up to 100 times faster than usual. The surge often progresses along a glacier
                line     like a great wave, proceeding from one section to another. Subglacial streams of meltwater
                (5)      water pressure under the glacier might lift it off its bed, overcoming the friction between ice
                and rock, thus freeing the glacier, which rapidly sliders downhill Surge glaciers also might
                be influenced by the climate, volcanic heat, or earthquakes. However, many of these
                glaciers exist in the same area as normal glaciers, often almost side by side.
                
                (10)              Some 800 years ago, Alaska’s Hubbard Glacier advanced toward the sea, retreated, and
                advanced again 500 years later. Since 1895, this seventy-mile-long river of ice has been
                flowing steadily toward the Gulf of Alaska at a rate of approximately 200 feet per year. In
                June 1986, however, the glacier surged ahead as much as 47 feet a day. Meanwhile, a
                western tributary, called Valerie Glacier, advanced up to 112 feet a day. Hubbard’s surge
                (15)    closed off Russell Fiord with a formidable ice dam, some 2,500 feet wide and up to 800
                feet high, whose caged waters threatened the town of Yakutat to the south.
                
                About 20 similar glaciers around the Gulf of Alaska are heading toward the sea. If
                enough surge glaciers reach the ocean and raise sea levels, West Antarctic ice shelves could
                rise off the seafloor and become adrift. A flood of ice would then surge into the Southern
                (20)    Sea. With the continued rise in sea level, more ice would plunge into the ocean, causing sea
                levels to rise even higher, which in turn would release more ice and set in motion a vicious
                cycle. The additional sea ice floating toward the tropics would increase Earth’s Albedo and
                lower global temperatures, perhaps enough to initiate a new ice age. This situation appears
                to have occurred at the end of the last warm interglacial (the time between glacations),
                (25)    called the Sangamon, when sea ice cooled the ocean dramatically, spawning the beginning
                of the Ice Age.
                
               
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                
                
                
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>  Mary Goddard first got into printing at the age of twenty-four when her brother
                opened a printing shop in Providence, Rhode Island, in 1762. When he proceeded to
                get into trouble with his partners and creditors, it was Mary Goddard and her mother
                 who were left to run the shop. In 1765 they began publishing the Providence Gazette, a
                weekly newspaper. Similar problems seemed to follow her brother as he opened
                businesses in Philadelphia and again in Baltimore. Each time Ms. Goddard was
                brought in to run the newspapers. After starting Baltimore's first newspaper, The
                Maryland Journal, in 1773, her brother went broke trying to organize a colonial postal
                service. While he was in debtor's prison. Mary Katherine Goddard's name appeared on
                the newspaper's masthead for the first time.
                
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>

            <sentence>
                <sentenceText> Mary Goddard first got into printing at the age of twenty-four when her brother
                    opened a printing shop in Providence, Rhode Island, in 1762.</sentenceText>
                <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                <context>no</context>
                <assertion>agentGoal(woman, printer)</assertion>
                
            </sentence>
            </sentences>

        </paragraph>
        
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>   When the Continental Congress fled there from Philadelphia in 1776, it
                commissioned Ms. Goddard to print the first official version of the Declaration of
                Independence in January 1777. After printing the documents, she herself paid the post
                riders to deliver the Declaration throughout the colonies.
                
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>

            <sentence>
                <sentenceText> Within a few years the horse - drawn trolleys were retired and electric streetcar networks crisscrossed and connected every major urban area, fostering a wave of suburbanization that transformed the compact industrial city into a dispersed metropolis.</sentenceText>
                <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                <context>no</context>
                <assertion>agentGoal(woman, deliverDeclarationIndependence)</assertion>
                
            </sentence>
            </sentences>

        </paragraph>

<paragraph>
    <id_paragraph>4</id_paragraph>
    <paragraphText>    During the American Revolution, Mary Goddard continued to publish Baltimore's
        only newspaper, which one historian claimed was "second to none among the
        colonies". She was also the city's postmaster from 1775 to 1789 - appointed by
        Benjamin Franklin - and is considered to be the first woman to hold a federal position.
        
        
        
    </paragraphText>
    <sentences>
        
        
    </sentences>
    
</paragraph>


    </paragraphs>
    
    
    <questionAnswerBlock>
        <questions>
            <question>
                <questionText>TThe word “intervals” in line 2 is closest in meaning to
                    (A) records	(B) speeds	(C) distances	(D) periods
                    
                    32. The author compares the surging motion of a surge glacier to the movement of a
                    (A) fish	(B) wave	(C) machine	(D) boat
</questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   influenced
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>announced
                          
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>property</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(heralded,announced)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   rejected		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>ignored		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
            <question>
                <questionText> The word "position" in line 24 is closest in meaning to
                  
                   
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>    job
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>activity</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(position,job)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> election
                           
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion> no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> document	 		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> location		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
        </questions>
    </questionAnswerBlock>
</passage>

<!--- pasaje 35 -->
<passage>
    <description>
        <idPassage>35</idPassage>
        <documentType>argumentative</documentType>
        <area>astronomy</area>
        <topic>galaxies</topic>
    </description>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>          Galaxies are the major building blocks of the universe. A galaxy is giant family of
                many millions of stars, and it is held together by its own gravitational field. Most of the
                material universe is organized into galaxies of stars together with gas and dust.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                <sentence>
                    <sentenceText>Galaxies are the major building blocks of the universe. </sentenceText>
                    <semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>hyponym(UniversebuildingBlocks,galaxies)</assertion>
                    
                    
                </sentence>
              
              <sentence>
                  <sentenceText>A galaxy is giant family of
                      many millions of stars, and it is held together by its own gravitational field. </sentenceText>
                  <semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
                  <context>no</context>
                  <assertion>hyponym(starsGiantFamily,galaxies)</assertion>
                  
                  
              </sentence>


            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        
        
        
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>          There are three main types of galaxy: spiral, elliptical, and irregular. The Milky
                Way is a spiral galaxy, a flattish disc of stars with two spiral arms emerging from its
                central nucleus. About one-quarter of all galaxies have this shape. Spiral galaxies are
                well supplied with the interstellar gas in which new stars form: as the rotating spiral
                pattern sweeps around the galaxy it compresses gas and dust, triggering the formation
                of bright young stars and in its arms. The elliptical galaxies have a symmetrical elliptical or
                spheroidal shape with no obvious structure. Most of their member stars are very old
                and since ellipticals are devoid of interstellar gas, no new stars are forming in them.
                The biggest and brightest galaxies in the universe are ellipticals with masses of about
                1013 times that of the Sun, these giants may frequently be sources of strong radio
                emission, in which case they are called radio galaxies. About two-thirds of all galaxies
                are elliptical. Irregular galaxies comprise about one-tenth of all galaxies and they come
                in many subclasses.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                <sentence>
                    <sentenceText>There are three main types of galaxy: spiral, elliptical, and irregular.</sentenceText>
                    <semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>hyponym(galaxy,spiralGalaxy)</assertion>
                     <assertion>hyponym(galaxy,elliptical)</assertion>
                     <assertion>hyponym(galaxy,irregularGalaxy)</assertion>
                    
                </sentence>
                <sentence>
                    <sentenceText>The Milky
                        Way is a spiral galaxy, a flattish disc of stars with two spiral arms emerging from its
                        central nucleus.</sentenceText>
                    <semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>hyponym(spiralGalaxy,milkyWayGalaxy)</assertion>
                    <semanticRelation>PartWhole/ObjectComponent</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>component(spiralGalaxy, flattish disc)</assertion>
                      <assertion>component(spiralGalaxy, spiralArms)</assertion>
                        <assertion>component(spiralGalaxy, centralNucleus)</assertion>
                </sentence>


                
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>         Measurement in space is quite different from measurement on Earth. Some
                terrestrial distances can be expressed as intervals of time, the time to fly from one
                continent to another or the time it takes to drive to work, for example. By comparison
                with these familiar yardsticks, the distances to the galaxies are incomprehensibly large,
                but they too are made more manageable by using a time calibration, in this case the
                distance that light travels in one year. On such a scale the nearest giant spiral galaxy,
                the Andromeda galaxy, is two million light years away. The most distant luminous
                objects seen by telescopes are probably ten thousand million light years away. Their
                light was already halfway here before the Earth even formed. The light from the nearby
                Virgo galaxy set out when reptiles still dominated the animal world.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                
                
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        
        
    </paragraphs>
    
    
    <questionAnswerBlock>
        <questions>
            
            <question>
                <questionText> The word "major" in line 1 is closest in meaning to
                    

                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   intense
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(position,job)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>  principal
                            
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion> no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> huge		 		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        
                        <assertion>synonym(major,huge)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> unique		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
            
            <question>
                <questionText> The word "obvious" in line 10 is closest in meaning to
                  

                    
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>      discovered
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>shape</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(obvious,discovered)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> apparent
                            
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion> no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> understood		 		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>  simplistic		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>

                    </questions>
    </questionAnswerBlock>
</passage>

<!--- pasaje 36 -->

<passage>
    <description>
        <idPassage>36</idPassage>
        <documentType>argumentative</documentType>
        <area>history</area>
        <topic>railroad</topic>
    </description>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>         Before the mid-1860's, the impact of the railroads in the United States was limited,
                in the sense that the tracks ended at the Missouri River, approximately the centers of the
                country. At that point the trains turned their freight, mail, and passengers over to
                steamboats, wagons, and stagecoaches. This meant that wagon freighting, stagecoaching
                and steamboating did not come to an end when the first train appeared; rather they
                became supplements or feeders. Each new "end-of-track" became a center for animaldrawn
                or waterborne transportation. The major effect of the railroad was to shorten the
                distance that had to be covered by the older, slower, and more costly means. Wagon
                freighters continued operating throughout the 1870's and 1880's and into the 1890's,
                although over constantly shrinking routes, and coaches and wagons continued to
                crisscross the West wherever the rails had not yet been laid.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                <sentence>
                    <sentenceText> The major effect of the railroad was to shorten the
                        distance that had to be covered by the older, slower, and more costly means.</sentenceText>
                    <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/CauseEffect</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>effect(railroad, reduceDistance)</assertion>
                    
                    
                </sentence>
              
                
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText> The beginning of a major change was foreshadowed in the later 1860's, when the
                Union Pacific Railroad at last began to build westward from the Central Plaints city of
                Omaha to meet the Central Pacific Railroad advancing eastward form California through
                the formidable barriers of the Sierra Nevada. Although President Abraham Lincoln
                signed the original Pacific Railroad bill in 1862 and a revised, financially much more
                generous version in 1864, little construction was completed until 1865 on the Central
                Pacific and 1866 on the Union Pacific. The primary reason was skepticism that a
                railroad built through so challenging and thinly settled a stretch of desert, mountain,
                and semiarid plain could pay a profit. In the words of an economist, this was a case of
                "premature enterprise", where not only the cost of construction but also the very high
                risk deterred private investment. In discussing the Pacific Railroad bill, the chair of the
                congressional committee bluntly stated that without government subsidy no one would
                undertake so unpromising a venture; yet it was a national necessity to link East and
                West together.
                
            </paragraphText>
            
            <sentence>
                <sentenceText> The primary reason was skepticism that a
                    railroad built through so challenging and thinly settled a stretch of desert, mountain,
                    and semiarid plain could pay a profit. </sentenceText>
                <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/CauseEffect</semanticRelation>
                <context>no</context>
                <assertion>effect(railroad, skepticism)</assertion>
                
            </sentence>
        </paragraph>
        
    </paragraphs>
    
    
    <questionAnswerBlock>
        <questions>
            <question>
                <questionText>The word "supplements" in line 6 is closest in meaning to
                    
                    
                    
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> extensions
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(suplements,extensions)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> reformers
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>  dependents	 	</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>influences		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
            <question>
                <questionText> The word "subsidy" in line 23 is closest in meaning to
                   
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   persuasion
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> financing
                            
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>support</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(subsidy,financing)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>  explanation		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> penalty			</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
        </questions>
    </questionAnswerBlock>
</passage>

<!--- pasaje 37 -->

<passage>
    <description>
        <idPassage>37</idPassage>
        <documentType>expository</documentType>
        <area>history</area>
        <topic>numbers</topic>
    </description>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>          Humanity's primal efforts to systematize the concepts of size, shapes, and number
                are usually regarded as the earliest mathematics. However, the concept of number and
                the counting process developed so long before the time of recorded history (there is
                archaeological evidence that counting was employed by humans as far back as 50,000
                years ago) that the manner of this development is largely conjectural. Imaging how it
                probably came about is not difficult. The argument that humans, even in prehistoric
                times, had some number sense, at least to the extent of recognizing the concepts of
                more and less when some objects were added to or taken away from a small group,
                seems fair, for studies have shown that some animal possess such a sense.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
               
               
                
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>  With the gradual evolution of society, simple counting became imperative. A tribe
                had to know how many members it had and how many enemies, and shepherd needed
                to know if the flock of sheep was decreasing in size. Probably the earliest way of keeping
                a count was by some simple tally method, employing the principle of one-to-one
                correspondence. In keeping a count of sheep, for example, one finger per sheep could
                be turned under. Counts could also be maintained by making scratches in the dirt or on
                a stone, by cutting notches in a piece of wood, or by tying knots in a string.
                
              
                
            </paragraphText>
            
            <sentence>
                <sentenceText> A tribe had to know how many members it had and how many enemies, and shepherd needed
                    to know if the flock of sheep was decreasing in size.</sentenceText>
                <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/AgentGoal</semanticRelation>
                <context>no</context>
                <assertion>agentGoal(tribu, enemiesCounting)</assertion>
                <assertion>agentGoal(tribu, membersCounting)</assertion>
                <assertion>agentGoal(shepherd, sheepCounting)</assertion>
               
                
            </sentence>
        </paragraph>
        
        
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>
                
                Then, perhaps later, an assortment of vocal sounds was developed as a word tally
                against the number of objects in a small group. And still later, with the refinement of
                writing, a set of signs was devised to stand for these numbers. Such an imagined
                development is supported by reports of anthropologists in their studies of present-day
                societies that are thought to be similar to those of early humans.
                
            </paragraphText>
            
            
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
    
    
    <questionAnswerBlock>
        <questions>
            <question>
                <questionText>The word "conjectural" in line 5 is closest in meaning to
                    
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> complex
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>based on guessing
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>property</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>     unbelievable
	</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> supported by careful research		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(conjectural,supported)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
            <question>
                <questionText> Which of the following is NOT mentioned as an early methods of counting?
                    
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>  Cutting notches
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>colectionMember(countingMethods,cuttingNotches)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> Bending fingers
                           
                            
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   piling stones				</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        
                        <assertion>colectionMember(countingMethods,pilingStones)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> Tying knots 		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>PartWhole/CollectionMember</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>colectionMember(countingMethods,tyingKnots)</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
        </questions>
    </questionAnswerBlock>
</passage>

<!--- pasaje 38 -->

<passage>
    <description>
        <idPassage>38</idPassage>
        <documentType>narrative</documentType>
        <area>history</area>
        <topic>mining</topic>
    </description>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>1</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText>          As the merchant class expanded in the eighteenth-century North American colonies,
                the silversmith and the coppersmith businesses rose to serve it. Only a few silversmiths
                were available in New York or Boston in the late seventeenth century, but in the
                eighteenth century they could be found in all major colonial cities. No other colonial
                 artisans rivaled the silversmiths' prestige. They handled the most expensive materials
                and possessed direct connections to prosperous colonies merchants. Their products,
                primarily silver plates and bowls, reflected their exalted status and testified to their
                customers' prominence.
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
                <sentence>
                    <sentenceText> Their products,
                        primarily silver plates and bowls, reflected their exalted status and testified to their
                        customers' prominence.
</sentenceText>
                    <semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
                    <context>no</context>
                    <assertion>hyponym(miningProduct,plate)</assertion>
                    <assertion>hyponym(miningProduct,bowl)</assertion>
                    
                    
                </sentence>
               
              
                
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>2</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText> Silver stood as one of the surest ways to store wealth at a time before neighborhood
                banks existed. Unlike the silver coins from which they were made, silver articles were
                readily identifiable. Often formed to individual specifications, they always carried the
                silversmith's distinctive markings and consequently could be traced and retrieved.
                Customers generally secured the silver for the silver objects they ordered. They
                saved coins, took them to smiths, and discussed the type of pieces they desired.
                Silversmiths complied with these requests by melting the money in a small furnace,
                adding a bit of copper to form a stronger alloy, and casting the alloy in rectangular
                blocks. They hammered these ingots to the appropriate thickness by hand, shaped
                them, and pressed designs into them for adornment. Engraving was also done by hand.
                In addition to plates and bowls, some customers sought more intricate products, such as
                silver teapots. These were made by shaping or casting parts separately and then
                soldering them together.
                
                
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
            <sentence>
                <sentenceText>  In addition to plates and bowls, some customers sought more intricate products, such as
                    silver teapots.</sentenceText>
                <semanticRelation>ClassInclusion/Hyponym</semanticRelation>
                <context>no</context>
                <assertion>hyponym(miningProduct,teapots)</assertion>
            </sentence>
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
        
        <paragraph>
            <id_paragraph>3</id_paragraph>
            <paragraphText> Colonial coppersmithing also came of age in the early eighteenth century and
                prospered in northern cities. Copper's ability to conduct heat efficiently and to resist
                corrosion contributed to its attractiveness. But because it was expensive in colonial
                America, coppersmiths were never very numerous. Virtually all copper worked by
                smiths was imported as sheets or obtained by recycling old copper goods. Copper was
                used for practical items, but it was not admired for its beauty. Coppersmiths employed
                it to fashion pots and kettles for the home. They shaped it in much the same manner as
                silver or melted it in a foundry with lead or tin. They also mixed it with zinc to make
                brass for maritime and scientific instruments.
                
            </paragraphText>
            <sentences>
            
            </sentences>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
    
    
    <questionAnswerBlock>
        <questions>
            <question>
                <questionText>The word "exalted" in line 7 is closest in meaning to
                   
                    
                    
                    
                </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>  unusual
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>uncertain
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   surprising		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> superior	</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>status</context>
                        <assertion>synonym(exalted,superior)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
            <question>
                <questionText> The passage mentions all of the following as uses for copper in colonial America EXCEPT
                                   </questionText>
                <answers>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   cooking pots
                            

                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/InstrumentGoal</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>instrumentGoal(copper,cookingPotsCreation)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> scientific instruments
                            
                            
                        </answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/InstrumentGoal</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>instrumentGoal(copper,scientificInstrumentsCreation)</assertion>
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText>   musical instruments				</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>Similar/Synonym</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>no</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    <answer>
                        <answerText> maritime instruments
		</answerText>
                        <semanticRelation>CausePurpose/InstrumentGoal</semanticRelation>
                        <context>no</context>
                        <assertion>instrumentGoal(copper,maritimeInstrumentsCreation)</assertion>
                        
                    </answer>
                    
                </answers>
            </question>
        </questions>
    </questionAnswerBlock>
</passage>

<!--- pasaje 39 -->



</passages>